<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>

<book lang="en">
<bookinfo>
    <title>Introduction to Kubernetes HOL-1289</title>
    <author>
        <firstname>TBD, SUSE &lt; TBD &gt;</firstname>
    </author>
    <authorinitials>{</authorinitials>
<orgname>SUSE</orgname>
</bookinfo>
<chapter id="_ramping_up_to_the_fastlane_a_beginner_8217_s_guide_to_learning_and_using_kubernetes">
<title>Ramping up to the Fastlane: A Beginner&#8217;s Guide to Learning and Using Kubernetes</title>
<simpara>Emerging as the defacto standard of orchestrating containerized, microservice workloads, Kubernetes is quickly becoming a fundamental training goala. In this hands-on session, you will learn how to effectively utilize the Kubernetes technology across the various Dev, Security, Data, and Ops perspectives. Starting with a single workload and then working towards a complete, containerized service deployment, you will interact with and explore the features provided by Kubernetes to leverage the scalable, resilient, manageable environment for the workloads.</simpara>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_start_your_engines">
<title>Start Your Engines</title>
<simpara>A simple deployment of a set of containers to show the value of Kubernetes orchestration.</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Goal / Objectives - Launch a complete Wordpress containerized, set of services
</simpara>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Process
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Follow these steps:
</simpara>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<simpara>
Login to your system ( user : geeko , password: linux )
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Launch a terminal, then from the command prompt, type
</simpara>
<screen>kubectl apply --filename="./Lab1/sample.yml"</screen>
<tip><simpara>as a reference, see <ulink url="https://kubernetes.io/docs/tutorials/stateful-application/mysql-wordpress-persistent-volume/">Sample</ulink>.</simpara></tip>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Then get a glimpse of what you just launched, via
</simpara>
<screen>kubectl get pods --namespace="vroom" -o wide</screen>
<note><simpara>In later exercises, we will show other ways to interact with and view what is running.</simpara></note>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
You can now stop all of these deployed microservices, via
</simpara>
<screen>kubectl delete --filename="./Lab1/sample.yml"</screen>
<simpara>and check that they are gone, via</simpara>
<screen>kubectl get pods --namespace="vroom"</screen>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
As bonus exercises, try
</simpara>
<screen>man kubectl
kubectl --help
man kubectl-get</screen>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>Woohoo !</emphasis></emphasis> Now you can see the initial appeal of what Kubernetes offers, leveraging the predominant CLI tool, <literal>kubectl</literal> ( controls the Kubernetes cluster manager ).</simpara>
<note><simpara>The example commands provided in this exercise used the full syntax and option names. In later exercises we will show the alternatives.</simpara></note>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Knowledge Check:
</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
ability to deploy multiple microservices with a single command
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
getting the status of those microservices, using a variation of that single command
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
destroy the set of microservices, again using a variation of that single command
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_turn_signal_on_getting_ready_to_merge">
<title>Turn Signal On, Getting Ready to Merge</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Understanding the basics of how to interact
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_heading_down_the_highway">
<title>Heading Down the Highway</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Becoming aware of all the aspects around you
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_summary">
<title>Summary</title>
<simpara>At this point you should now feel like you have enough experience with Kubernetes to share with your peers, begin using it on-premise, in managed services or in public cloud providers.</simpara>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_homework">
<title>Homework</title>
<simpara>If this enticed you to further investigate this technology, feel free to grab all of the lab exercises, plus the technology to deploy your own Kubernetes cluster.</simpara>
</chapter>
</book>
