<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>

<book lang="en">
<bookinfo>
    <title>Introduction to Kubernetes HOL-1289</title>
    <author>
        <firstname>TBD, SUSE &lt; TBD &gt;</firstname>
    </author>
    <authorinitials>{</authorinitials>
<orgname>SUSE</orgname>
</bookinfo>
<chapter id="_ramping_up_to_the_fastlane_a_beginner_8217_s_guide_to_learning_and_using_kubernetes">
<title>Ramping up to the Fastlane: A Beginner&#8217;s Guide to Learning and Using Kubernetes</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Emerging as the defacto standard of orchestrating containerized, microservice workloads, Kubernetes is quickly becoming a fundamental training goala. In this hands-on session, you will learn how to effectively utilize the Kubernetes technology across the various Dev, Security, Data, and Ops perspectives. Starting with a single workload and then working towards a complete, containerized service deployment, you will interact with and explore the features provided by Kubernetes to leverage the scalable, resilient, manageable environment for the workloads.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<section id="_start_your_engines">
<title>Start Your Engines</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Let us get started with a quick, simple interaction with Kubernetes
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
<section id="_turn_signal_on_getting_ready_to_merge">
<title>Turn Signal On, Getting Ready to Merge</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Understanding the basics of how to interact
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
<section id="_heading_down_the_highway">
<title>Heading Down the Highway</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Becoming aware of all the aspects around you
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_summary">
<title>Summary</title>
<simpara>At this point you should now feel like you have enough experience with Kubernetes to share with your peers, begin using it on-premise, in managed services or in public cloud providers.</simpara>
</chapter>
</book>
