<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>

<book lang="en">
<bookinfo>
    <title>SAP<superscript>&#174;</superscript> Data Hub on SUSE<superscript>&#174;</superscript> Container as a Service Platform</title>
    <author>
        <firstname>Alex Arnoldy, SUSE &lt; alex.arnoldy@suse.com &gt;</firstname>
    </author>
    <authorinitials>{</authorinitials>
<orgname>SUSE</orgname>
</bookinfo>
<chapter id="_revision_history">
<title>Revision History</title>
<table
frame="all"
rowsep="1" colsep="1"
>
<title>Revisions</title>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colname="col_1" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="col_2" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="col_3" colwidth="33*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top">Version </entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top">Date         </entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top">Comments</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>0.5</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>01/15/19</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Initial draft</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>0.6</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>02/11/19</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Collaborative draft</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1.0</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>03/05/19</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>First draft to be shared with HPE as SUSE Company Confidential</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1.1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>03/31/19</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Proposed hardware config - shared w/ HPE as SUSE Company Confidential</simpara></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<simpara><emphasis>*DRAFT COPY - DO NOT PUBLISH*</emphasis></simpara>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<simpara>Enterprise data is exploding and is both a challenge and an opportunity. Companies are discovering ways to transform their data into services that help differentiate the business and create new lines of revenue.  Unfortunately, managing and fully utilizing the information stored in data silos (e.g. cloud databases, Hadoop clusters, social media feeds) has become incredibly complex due to requirements for security, governance, and specialized training.  <ulink url="https://www.sap.com/products/data-hub.html">SAP Data Hub</ulink> provides a GUI-based business-wide view of a broad array of data systems, databases, and assets to enable your analytics and business intelligence teams to manage your entire data landscape through an intuitive “single pane of glass”.    In what is likely to become a trend, SAP mandates that this application is deployed on a Kubernetes compatible container platform. <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/caas-platform/">SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform</ulink> enables you to extend your SUSE Enterprise Linux for SAP environment to container-based application delivery.</simpara>
<section id="_target_audience">
<title>Target Audience</title>
<simpara>This discussion will be of interest to professionals involved in both IT Operations and Analytics/Business Intelligence.   The recommended framework supplies the requirements to implement SAP’s Data Hub that is certified on SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform.</simpara>
</section>
<section id="_business_problem">
<title>Business Problem</title>
<simpara>Today&#8217;s business leaders are under increasing pressure to drive their business with data driven decisions. This presents a particular challenge for those executives who strive to bring together the right combination of disparate data sources to unlock new value for the business.</simpara>
<simpara>This difficulty is compounded by the very nature of how data is collected and stored, which results in independent data silos with no easy way to make critical associations across them. These data silos may be stored geographically close together, or far apart. Some may be built with on premise resources, and some housed in one or more public clouds. Valuable data is often found in structured and unstructured databases, Hadoop data lakes, data warehouses, and even in text files. Gaining new insights into potential customers and business opportunities may involve nearly all of the data silos a company has available to it.</simpara>
<figure id="img-Data_Pipeline_Funnel"><title>SAP Data Hub Data Pipeline Funnel</title>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="Data_Funnel_Pipeline.png"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>SAP_Data_Hub_Data_Pipeline_Funnel</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<simpara>What&#8217;s more, finding a business application to perform the task is not even the hardest part. Businesses need to ensure their data analysis software investment can meet the scale of their current, as well as their future application/data landscape, plus enforce data governance. Equally as important is the resiliency and scalability of the underlying infrastructure. Experienced leaders know that Enterprise grade software is a poor investment if it is not built on Enterprise grade infrastructure.</simpara>
</section>
<section id="_business_value">
<title>Business Value</title>
<simpara>SAP Data Hub is a containerized solution designed to be deployed on Enterprise grade Kubernetes clusters such as SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform (See <emphasis role="strong"><phrase role=".underline">SAP Note 2693555</phrase></emphasis> for certified systems). For more than 17 years SAP has developed their software on SUSE Linux Enterprise Server (SLES) and SUSE solutions such as SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform.</simpara>
<simpara>SAP Data Hub is built on a next generation data aggregation model that does away with the need for expensive data warehouses. Instead, SAP Data Hub allows data extraction and formatting to be done on the platform where the data resides. This is in contrast to the current practice of using cumbersome, single-use Extract, Load,  Transform (ELT) operations that are used to populate data warehouses; SAP Data Hub provides formatted, refined and cleansed data from multiple sources directly to the data consumers.</simpara>
<simpara>SAP Data Hub leverages data pipelines, which are built from reusable application components. Data pipelines are computational models that are executed natively on the data source. They define what data should be gathered from which sources, and how that data should be formatted at the source. Pipelines also specify what refinements and cleansing each stream of data should go through to make it compatible with the other data streams in the pipeline. Finally, they identify to which consumer or consumers the collated data should be sent. Since SAP Data Hub does not need persist data, it completely eliminates the need for expensive, scale-limiting data warehouses.</simpara>
<simpara>Data pipelines can be created through a graphical user interface to leverage existing data sources such as SAP HANA, SAP Vora, Apache Spark, and Apache Hadoop; as well as all major open and closed source OLTP, OLAP and NoSQL databases.</simpara>
<simpara>Before implementing a data analytics solution, you need to consider the specific problem you are working to solve. Below are some use cases that help you to zero in on the type of solution you are pursuing.</simpara>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_example_use_cases">
<title>Example Use Cases</title>
<simpara>This section will outline a few potential use cases for SAP Data Hub build on SUSE Containers as a Service Application Platform.   In general, SAP Data Hub exceeds in pulling information from multiple kinds of internal and external data resources to enable insight into very complex analytical problems.   The use of machine learing and Big Data analytics platforms like SAP, Hadoop, MapR, Cloudera, etc. require access to large pools of unstructured data in a systematic, highly automated, secure way.</simpara>
<section id="_fraud_detection">
<title>Fraud Detection</title>
<simpara>Credit card fraud has become an epidemic with losses in the billions of dollars.  Financial institutions need the ability to create profiles that alert to probable fraud on large volumes of transactions.   The more information they can cross-reference, the more accurate their models will become.  SAP Data Hub can pull in transactional data from ERP systems, credit reporting bureaus, email from a Hadoop cluster, social media data, and “Dark Web” databases to enable data scientist to build very precise detection methodologies.</simpara>
</section>
<section id="_manufacturing_equipment_maintenance">
<title>Manufacturing Equipment Maintenance</title>
<simpara>Global manufacturers rely on the uptime of their equipment to meet product delivery targets.   Unscheduled maintenance or equipment failure can result in lost profits, poor quality, and unmet commitments.   Conversely, over-scheduling maintenance activities also impacts cost and output.   Manufacturers were early adopters of Internet of Things (IOT) technology for the real time monitoring of equipment sensors (e.g. temperature, vibration, humidity, motor loading, etc.)  to have a better understanding of the state of their environment.   What if predictive models and machine learning (ML) could be used to optimize maintenance scheduling?  SAP Data Hub can be used to orchestrate the end-to-end data flow to feed a ML platform to predict impending outages and schedule corrective maintenance before any disruptions.</simpara>
</section>
<section id="_customer_affinity_recommendations">
<title>Customer Affinity Recommendations</title>
<simpara>E-Commerce sites routinely use various data sources to try to recommend an additional purchase or fine-tune your search to more relevant items.   Early attempts were based solely on purchasing behavior at an individual retailer, but state of the art now requires data input from email, social media, browser search data, clickstream data, and credit card reporting sites.   SAP Data Hub enables you to easily build this pipeline to feed real time recommendations into an active session on a purchasing website for consideration.   This information can greatly increase the revenue per transaction metric that is critical to success.</simpara>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_requirements">
<title>Requirements</title>
<simpara>As an IT organization evaluates solutions to the data growth and migration challenge, key requirements will be defined. Below are some typical requirements that you will be considering as you experiment and evaluate software.</simpara>
<table
frame="all"
rowsep="1" colsep="1"
>
<title>Data Analytics Solution Requirements</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colname="col_1" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="col_2" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top">Requirement Type      </entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top">Details</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Existing Data Stores</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Access data from a variety of data sources, including Hadoop data lakes, object stores, databases, and data warehouses, both in the cloud and on-premise.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Perform data transformations, data quality, and data preparation processes.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Define data pipelines and streams.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Embed and productize scripts, programs, and algorithms of the Data Scientist.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Productize open libraries or ML algorithms in one framework.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Distributed Data Processing</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Distribute computational tasks to the native environments where the data reside.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Remote Process scheduling:</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>SAP Business Warehouse process chains.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>SAP Data Services dataflows.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>SAP HANA smart data integration Flowgraphs.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Governance</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Establish and manage zones in a landscape with attached policies and services levels.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Security and Access Control capabilities.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Orchestration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Workflow creation of operations and processes across the landscape with monitoring and analysis capabilities.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Execution of end-to-end data processes, starting with the ingestion of data into the landscape (e.g. the data lake), including data processing, and leading up to the delivery or integration of the resulting data into enterprise processes and applications.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Data Ingestion and Processing</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Data integration, cleansing, enrichment, masking and anonymization.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Data Discovery</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Data Profiles for Big Data Sets showing quality and comprehensive structure information.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Ability to crawl, discover, and tag data elements.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Expose discovered data for further usage.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Scalability</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Scalable Architecture, from small to big, test to production deployment.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Deployment</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Easy deployment, using a proven-to-work combination of the several components.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Fault Tolerance</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Single component error will not lead to whole system unavailability.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Ease of Management/Ops</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Reduced complexity for solution management.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Physical Footprint</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Compact solution that works within your existing infrastructure models.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Flexibility</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Flexible building block approach allows sizing according to customer needs.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Security</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Solution provides means to secure customer infrastructure.</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>High performance</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Best practices are designed into the solution to ensure the best performance results.</simpara></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<simpara>With a solid understanding of your requirements, you can now begin to design the solution.  The following section will outline the key concepts in the software architecture of the SAP Data Hub reference configuration.</simpara>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_software_architecture">
<title>Software Architecture</title>
<section id="_sap_data_hub">
<title>SAP Data Hub</title>
<simpara>SAP Data Hub offers data management capabilities to help customers manage their growing amount of data. This solution combines data governance, management of data pipelines and data integration using a single visual interface and without the need of moving data into a central data warehouse.  <xref linkend="img-Solution_Architecture"/> shows a high-level view of the architectural components designed to handle a wide range of enterprise applications scenarios.  The optional Hadoop cluster can be used as the main software platform for handling composition of application data.</simpara>
<figure id="img-Solution_Architecture"><title>SAP Data Hub Architecture</title>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="SAP_HANA_Architecture.png"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>SAP_Data_Hub_Architecture</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Tenant Applications and Services
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Tenant Applications and Services are the core of SAP Data Hub. SAP Data Hub provides various tools for development and administration, as well as applications that are accessible through the SAP Data Hub application launchpad. SAP Data Hub Pipelines are the connectors between the various SAP Data Hub data sources. They provide reusable, configurable operations to process data from the various sources,including CSV files, web services APIs as well as SAP’s own data stores and can be flexibly designed. The SAP Data Hub Modeler allows the creation and configuration of such pipelines through a graphical user interface. The Metadata Explorer provides information about the location, attributes, quality, and sensitivity of data. With this information, you can make informed decisions about which datasets to publish and determine who has access to use or view information about the datasets.  The Connection Management block enables connections to managed systems or external storage. Services such as Amazon S3, Google Cloud Services, Microsoft Azure (ADL, WASB),Data services, or Hadoop HDFS can be connected, as well as databases (Oracle, SAP HANA, SAP VORA) or business warehouses (SAP BW).
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
SAP Vora Distributed Database
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
SAP Vora is a horizontally scalable, distributed database which can store and process structured data, time-series data (i.e. IoT streams), graph data and semi-structured documents in-memory and/or on disk. SAP Vora is only available with SAP Data Hub, running in Kubernetes as a fully containerized application. It can store analytics data in Kubernetes pods as well as provide a bi-directional Spark2 interface between SAP Data Hub and an optionally co-located Hadoop cluster. Like SAP Data Hub, Vora requires a Kubernetes cluster of at least three Worker Nodes, but runs alongside Data Hub on the same cluster.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
SAP HANA (Internal)
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
SAP HANA is SAP&#8217;s premiere, in-memory database. HANA provides ultra-low latency performance for OLTP and OLAP environments. SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP has specific enhancements for Enterprise class SAP applications, including SAP HANA. Deploying an Enterprise SAP HANA database on SLES for SAP allows for important enhancements in terms of availability, security, data encryption, and hardware support (such as NV-DIMMs). An important aspect of SAP Data Hub is that it leverages a small, containerized SAP HANA database for managing Data Hub metadata. No installation, maintenance, or sizing considerations are required for this HANA instance.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Container Registry
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
SAP Data Hub requires a Docker repository for container images. This can be a publicly accessible site or a private collection of workload images. Other public or private registry sites can be used to provide files like Helm charts to deploy complete services. Although the private Docker registry is not part of the SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform, you can either build an on-premise instance using the Containers Module Add-on included with SUSE Linux Enterprise Sever for SAP along with the SUSE Portus (<ulink url="http://port.us.org">http://port.us.org</ulink>) package or deploying this as a container directly on SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform.  Portus is an open source on-premise authorization service that allows users to administrate and secure their Docker registries with fine grained control.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Optional Hadoop Cluster
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
An optional Hadoop cluster can be built on dedicated nodes and co-located with SAP Data Hub. This associated Hadoop Data Lake can be used as a local computational/storage medium for SAP Data Hub original and uploaded content. The SAP Data Hub Spark Extensions are used to interface with the Spark2 environment on the Hadoop cluster for processing and storing data.  When utilizing this cluster, Data Hub users can leverage the analytical strengths of SAP Vora to analyze and store data in HDFS through the SAP Data Hub Vora Spark Extension. SUSE has extensive experience deploying bare-metal and virtualized Hadoop clusters on SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. While this Hadoop cluster uses dedicated nodes, its HDFS storage is built on block storage from the <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-enterprise-storage/">SUSE Enterprise Storage</ulink> storage cluster that also serves SAP Data Hub.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>
<section id="_suse_sap_data_hub_with_suse_caas_platform">
<title>SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform</title>
<simpara>SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform is an integrated software platform which automates the tasks of building, managing and upgrading Kubernetes clusters. It combines the benefits of an enterprise-ready operating system with the agility of an orchestration platform for containerized applications such as SAP Data Hub.</simpara>
<simpara>While there are several top tier Kubernetes offerings in the market, SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform stands out for its ease of installation and configuration, DevOps integration (via <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/cloud-application-platform/">SUSE Cloud Application Platform</ulink>), and enterprise level of operability and scalability.</simpara>
<simpara>One of the biggest challenges for Kubernetes operators is matching the scalability of the node level infrastructure with that of the overlaying container infrastructure. Inconsistently applied software changes as well as node configuration drift create ticking time bombs in production Kubernetes clusters.</simpara>
<simpara>SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform (<xref linkend="img-CaaSP_Detailed_Architecture"/>) resolves these problems with a combination of SUSE MicroOS as the container host operating system and Salt for configuration management. SUSE MicroOS is a mission-specific derivative of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server (SLES). While MicroOS leverages the same codebase and packages, its implementation ensures that software changes are applied atomically and within a snapshot-protected environment. The combination of MicroOS and Salt guarantees that all nodes in a cluster are always in a known and consistent state. The troubleshooting nightmares of discovering a single node with a partially-failed configuration or software change are a thing of the past.</simpara>
<figure id="img-CaaSP_Detailed_Architecture"><title>SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform Architecture</title>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="CaaSP_Detailed_Architecture.png"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>CaaSP_Detailed_Architecture</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<simpara>A SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform (<xref linkend="img-CaaSP_Nodes"/>) consists of the following node types:</simpara>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform Administration Node
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The Administration Node of the SUSE {Product Name} manages the deployment of the cluster and runs central services like:
</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<emphasis role="strong">Velum</emphasis>: Web-UI dashboard used to administer the cluster.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<emphasis role="strong">Salt Master</emphasis>:  Manages the configuration of the cluster nodes.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<emphasis role="strong">MariaDB Database</emphasis>: Stores Velum data and Salt master daemon events
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<emphasis role="strong">Dex Identity Service</emphasis>: Provides user authentication and a robust role-based access control (RBAC) system.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform Kubernetes Master Nodes
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform Master Nodes maintain the Kubernetes control plane services. These services run as containers on the Master Nodes. While three or more Master Nodes (always an odd number) are required for high availability of the Kubernetes control plane, a single Master Node is acceptable for demonstration purposes.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform Kubernetes Worker Nodes
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
The SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform Kubernetes Worker Nodes run the SAP Data Hub application containers. SAP Data Hub requires a minimum of three Kubernetes Worker Nodes (four worker nodes for production) and SUSE currently supports SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform clusters of up to 150 nodes. Additional Worker Nodes can be added to a Production SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform cluster non-disruptively.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<note><simpara>SAP specifies that each worker node must have a least 8 cores and 64GB of main memory.</simpara></note>
<figure id="img-CaaSP_Nodes"><title>SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform Node Configuration</title>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="CaaSP_Nodes.png"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>CaaSP_Nodes</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Optional SUSE Cloud Application Platform
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
SUSE Cloud Application Platform (CAP) is a DevOps toolset that speeds enterprise application development to container platforms. Referred to as a PaaS, or Platform-as-a-Service, SUSE Cloud Application Platform is the developer tools that allow rapid application development.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_storage_architecture">
<title>Storage Architecture</title>
<simpara>The storage layer of this solution leverages the Software Defined Storage capabilities of SUSE Enterprise Storage (SES). SES is a commercially supported distribution of the Ceph enterprise grade, scale out storage solution.</simpara>
<simpara>Ceph is a scale out, distributed object store which provides excellent performance, scalability and reliability. In most use cases clients use Linux kernel libraries to read and write object and block data directly to/from a storage node in the SES cluster. SES also provides gateway options to support data access via iSCSI, NFS, S3, and Swift protocols.</simpara>
<simpara>The storage capacity of the SES solution can be expanded easily by integrating additional storage nodes to the cluster. Exiting storage nodes will take care of redistributing the data to the newly added nodes without interrupting the availability of storage services to the clients.</simpara>
<simpara>SES provides a reliable, scalable storage layer for the complete solution that supports:
* Dynamically provisioned block storage volumes to the pods running on SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform
* (Optionally) Block storage volumes for the co-located Hadoop cluster nodes, if configured
* Object storage through an S3-API compatible interface for additional data storage and backups</simpara>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Dynamically Provisioned Storage Volumes
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
In addition to providing block storage to the optional Hadoop cluster, a pod running on SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform can gain access to dynamically provisioned Kubernetes persistent volumes (PV) through Kubernetes persistent volume claims (PVC). Persistent volumes are created as block devices in the supporting SES cluster. SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform uses persistent volume claims (PVC)s to obtain dynamically provisioned persistent volumes through the Software Defined Storage mechanisms in SES. When a PVC is removed, the persistent volume and its associated block storage device in SES are automatically removed.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<section id="_software_and_systems_management">
<title>Software and Systems Management</title>
<simpara>A scale-out SAP HANA model is utilized to handle rapid data growth. As your SAP environment expands, you will need a dependable method of updating your SAP HANA servers.  SUSE Manager enables you to efficiently manage a set of Linux systems and keep them up-to-date. The benefits in a SAP HANA scale-out setup are:</simpara>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Reduce Complexity of Managing SAP HANA Environments
</term>
<listitem>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Ensure consistent management of SAP HANA and all other cluster systems.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Manage your data environment across physical, virtual and cloud environments.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Manage your channels effectively.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Create/Manage Development, QA and Production Channels
</term>
<listitem>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Add and manage third-party channels.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Simplify compliance.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Audit the Patch Status for SAP HANA and Subsystems
</term>
<listitem>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Track the configuration changes and make sure all administrators have the right authority for changes.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Slash costs of ownership.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Automate System Management Tasks for SAP HANA and All Other Subsystems
</term>
<listitem>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Leverage a single web-based interface to see the status of all your servers.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Use your resources effectively.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_hardware_architecture">
<title>Hardware Architecture</title>
<simpara>This reference defines a private proof-of-concept cluster.  Other guides will address cloud-based and production environments.  The proof-of-concept cluster is a starting point for prototyping real-world applications that are meant to go into product.  As such, a proof-of-concept cluster can easily be grown into a production environment.  Further, a private deployment is useful for secure, in-house prototyping, but is also not restricted from using cloud-based applications and data.  SAP Data Hub can manage data from locations both behind the firewall and in the cloud.</simpara>
<simpara>The backbone of the application environment is the Kubernetes cluster, as implemented in the SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform software.  As described in the architecture section above, this cluster can be implemented on low-cost, commodity hardware, typicall 1U racked boxes with 2-socket processors.  The application environment reflects a key aspect of growth from prototyping to production.  In a PoC, there are typically few application containers, as developers are gaining experience building, deploying, and managing code as containers on the new software environment.  As such, there are less demands on the hardware for resources, particularly main memory.  Memory can easily be expanded, as the cluster needs grow.  Processor speed, on the other hand, is something to carefully consider.  It is not as easy to swap processors, so choosing a medium to high-end Xeon processor with many cores is a good idea.</simpara>
<simpara>It is recommended to start with a minimum 2-socket Xeon processor with 6 to 12 cores.  Memory can be a meager 32GB.  Local storage on the cluster is used primarily for the operating system and any application temporary data.  A common choice is a RAID1 configuration of operating system disks, each with a minimum of 256GB.  SSD is the recommended choice, as it speeds operations and doesn&#8217;t add considerable cost to the cluster in this case.  Networking is another key performance area, so 10GbE NICs are a minimum recommendation.  You can start with 1 NIC, but that is a bare minimum and 2 or more NICs will be needed for specific network requirements, based on your application needs.  In particular, high-bandwidth data pipelines will move lots of data to the cluster storage and can easily saturate a single NIC.  Consider mapping 1 high-speed NIC to those storage requirements.</simpara>
<simpara>As described in the SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform section above, a minimum of 5 nodes will be required: 1 as the administration node, 1 master node, and 3 worker nodes.  Any <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/yessearch/">SUSE YES</ulink> certified HPE platform can be used for the physical nodes of this deployment, as long as the certification refers to the major version of the underlying SUSE operating system required by the SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform release.</simpara>
<figure id="img-SAP-SUSE_DataHub_Arch_ProLiant"><title>SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform Architecture</title>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="SAP-SUSE-DataHub-Arch-ProLiant.png"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>ProLiant_DataHub_Arch</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<section id="_compute">
<title>Compute</title>
<simpara>One key benefit of a this data analytics implementation is that HPE industry-standard servers can fulfill each of the resource node&#8217;s computational needs. To reduce the time spent on hardware specification for an initial proof of concept implementation, the hardware should be general purpose and allow for a wide range of configuration options. The industry leading HPE ProLiant rack mount servers with their high performance, multitude of network options and low energy consumption characteristics are ideal virtualization and storage nodes.</simpara>
<simpara>For this the implementation, HPE ProLiant DL360 servers were utilized for all node roles. The main distinction is higher-end specifications for the compute node, with more CPU cores and higher amounts of RAM, to host the required workloads.</simpara>
<simpara>The following considerations for the system platforms should be attended to:</simpara>
<note><simpara>Any <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/yessearch/">SUSE YES</ulink> certified HPE platform, like the HPE ProLiant DL360, can be used for the physical nodes of this deployment, as long as the certification refers to the major version of the underlying SUSE operating system required by the SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform release.</simpara></note>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Ensure that all similar system devices are consistent and up-to-date with regard to BIOS/uEFI/device firmware versions to reduce potential troubleshooting issues later
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Reset the BIOS setup configuration to the default setting to have a known baseline configuration to provide consistency.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
If possible, setup RAID1 mirroring on the storage controller across a pair of drives for the operating system installation
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<tip><simpara>HPE OneView can be setup with Server Profile Templates to apply to the various node roles and consistently deliver platform systems into a known state.</simpara></tip>
</section>
<section id="_storage">
<title>Storage</title>
<simpara>Discussed under the Storage Architecture section, the storage layer of this solution leverages the Software Defined Storage capabilities as provided by SUSE Enterprise Storage.</simpara>
<simpara>SAP Data Hub and SUSE CaaS Platform are the base framework for a data analytics environment.  The data analytics you execute will be defined by a set of application containers will run on the SUSE CaaS Platform.  These containers will access data across your company&#8217;s infrastructure and may store derived results in SUSE Enterprise Storage.  As you define the workflow of your data analytics applications, you will need to access data across many different storage system in your enterprise.  This access is beyond the scope of this architecture, but it is important to understand that data access will be required to a wide range of disparate storage systems.</simpara>
<simpara>The SUSE Enterprise Storage cluster can be utilized to store both intermediary and final results from the data analytics pipeline.  In other words, as your data analytics applications derive new data results, those are typically store in SUSE Enterprise Storage.  This allows the data analytics environment (SAP Data Hub, SUSE SAP Data Hub with SUSE CaaS Platform, and your data analytics applications) to be logically organized in one physical location.</simpara>
</section>
<section id="_network">
<title>Network</title>
<simpara>Networking is the technology component which typically requires the most advance planning.  Your data analytics applications will have unique network access requirements, especially when integrated with an existing IT infrastructure. For the physical level, using pairs of HPE FlexFabric Switch Series devices as top-of-rack (ToR) switches allows all servers, each having multiple 10GbE, or higher speed, NIC ports, to form a link aggregation group (LAG) across the ports with at least one NIC port on each switch in the stack. When using network interface bonding on the resource nodes, the LAG ideally offers switch redundancy within the rack and enables high availability throughout the infrastructure.</simpara>
<simpara>For this proof of concept deployment, a single 10GbE switch is used, having all resource nodes 10GbE NIC ports connected here, but could easily be expanded to the dual ToR configuration at a later date. To address management functions, the iLO, out-of-band interface can be connected to the same or another network switch infrastructure, but are fundamentally required to be accessible for the deployment.</simpara>
<simpara>The following considerations for the network switching configuration should be attended to:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Configure 802.3ad for system port bonding to get the maximum performance of bonded network interfaces
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Ensure that all similar switching devices are consistent and up-to-date with regard to firmware versions to reduce potential troubleshooting issues later.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter id="_bill_of_materials">
<title>Bill of Materials</title>
<simpara>The HPE ProLiant DL360 series Gen10 server is an excellent platform for a proof-of-concept implementation of SAP Data Hub on SUSE CaaS Platform software.  The DL360 provides powerful, dense compute and storage capabilities via the servers selected for this reference architecture.
And the ProLiant iLO management capability is a key piece of the management infrastructure for a data analytics cluster.</simpara>
<section id="_hpe_proliant_dl360_gen10_servers">
<title>HPE ProLiant DL360 Gen10 Servers</title>
<table
frame="all"
rowsep="1" colsep="1"
>
<title>Bill of Materials - HPE ProLiant DL360 Systems</title>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colname="col_1" colwidth="20*"/>
<colspec colname="col_2" colwidth="20*"/>
<colspec colname="col_3" colwidth="20*"/>
<colspec colname="col_4" colwidth="20*"/>
<colspec colname="col_5" colwidth="20*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>Role</emphasis></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>Quantity</emphasis></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>Product Number</emphasis></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>Product_Name</emphasis></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>Description</emphasis></emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Administration</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>755259-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>ProLiant DL360 Gen9</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE ProLiant DL360 Gen9 4LFF Configure-to-order Server HPE Dynamic Smart Array B140i, 4-Bay LFF Drive Cage</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>755382-L21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Processor</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Intel Xeon E5-2620v3 (2.4GHz/6-core/15MB/85W)</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>4</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>726718-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Memory</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>8GB (1x8GB) Single Rank x4 DDR4-2133 CAS-15-15-15 Registered Memory Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>665243-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Flexible LOM</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE Ethernet 10Gb 2-port 560FLR-SFP+ FIO Adapter</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>2</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>720478-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Power Supplies</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 500W Flex Slot Platinum Hot Plug Power supply Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>749974-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Storage Controller</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE Smart Array P440ar/2GB FBWC 12Gb 2-ports Int FIO SAS Controller</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>766211-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Storage cable</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE DL360 Gen9 LFF P440ar/H240ar SAS Cbl</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>2</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>652757-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Hard Drives</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 2TB 6G SAS 7.2K rpm LFF (3.5-inch) SC Midline 1yr Warranty Hard Drive</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>663202-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Rail Kit</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 1U Large Form Factor Ball Bearing Rail Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>663203-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Cable Management Arm</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 1U Cable Management Arm for Ball Bearing Rail Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Master</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>755259-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>ProLiant DL360 Gen9</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE ProLiant DL360 Gen9 4LFF Configure-to-order Server HPE Dynamic Smart Array B140i, 4-Bay LFF Drive Cage</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>755382-L21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Processor 1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Intel® Xeon® E5-2690v3 (2.6GHz/12-core/30MB/135W) FIO Processor Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>755382-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Processor 2</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Intel® Xeon® E5-2690v3 (2.6GHz/12-core/30MB/135W) FIO Processor Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>4</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>726718-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Memory for 1st processor</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>8GB (1x8GB) Single Rank x4 DDR4-2133 CAS-15-15-15 Registered Memory Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>4</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>726718-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Memory for 2nd processor</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>8GB (1x8GB) Single Rank x4 DDR4-2133 CAS-15-15-15 Registered Memory Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>665243-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>FlexibleLOM</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE Ethernet 10Gb 2-port 560FLR-SFP+ FIO Adapter</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>2</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>720478-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Power Supplies</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 800W Flex Slot Platinum Hot Plug Power Supply Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>4</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>765424-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Hard Drives</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 600GB 12G SAS 15K rpm LFF (3.5-inch) SC Enterprise 3yr Warranty Hard Drive</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>749974-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Storage Controller</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE Smart Array P440ar/2GB FBWC 12Gb 2-ports Int FIO SAS Controller</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>766211-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Storage Cable</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE DL360 Gen9 LFF P440ar/H240ar SAS Cbl</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>663202-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Rail Kit</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 1U Large Form Factor Ball Bearing Rail Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>663203-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Cable Management Arm</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 1U Cable Management Arm for Ball Bearing Rail Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Compute</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>3</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>755258-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>ProLiant DL360 Gen9</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE ProLiant DL360 Gen9 8SFF Configure-to-order Server HPE Dynamic Smart Array B140i, 8-Bay SFF Drive Cage</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>780003-L21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Processor 1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Intel® Xeon® E5-2699v3 (2.6GHz/18-core/45MB/145W) FIO Processor Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>780003-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Processor 2</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Intel® Xeon® E5-2699v3 (2.6GHz/18-core/45MB/145W) FIO Processor Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>4</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>726718-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Memory for 1st processor</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>8GB (1x8GB) Dual Rank x4 DDR4-2133 CAS-15-15-15 Registered Memory Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>4</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>726718-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Memory for 2nd processor</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>8GB (1x8GB) Dual Rank x4 DDR4-2133 CAS-15-15-15 Registered Memory Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>665243-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>FlexibleLOM</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE Ethernet 10Gb 2-port 560FLR-SFP+ FIO Adapter</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>2</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>720479-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Power Supply</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 800W Flex Slot Platinum Hot Plug Power Supply Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>6</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>759212-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Hard Drives</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 600GB 12G SAS 15K rpm SFF (2.5-inch) SC Enterprise 3yr Warranty Hard Drive</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>749974-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Storage Controller</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE Smart Array P440ar/2GB FBWC 12Gb 2-ports Int FIO SAS Controller</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>663201-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Rail Kit</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 1U SFF Ball Bearing Rail Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara></simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>1</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>663203-B21</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>Cable Management Arm</simpara></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top"><simpara>HPE 1U Cable Management Arm for Ball Bearing Rail Kit</simpara></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>
</chapter>
</book>
